Joe: Hello, my name is Joe
Beth: and I’m Beth
Joe: Welcome to our course
on Understanding Autism.
We will be with you throughout your
journey to provide some useful information
and clarify further, some of the elements
you will discover yourself along the way.
Beth: We also interview professionals
from the industry as we go, and
talk to some of the people who
live with Autism day to day.
All the way strengthening your
knowledge and helping you to become
more familiar with Autism and
pass this Level 2 certification.
So, let’s begin shall we?
Joe: First let’s start with
some broad strokes on Autism.
Autism spectrum disorder covers a wide
variation of symptoms and the severity of
those symptoms that can be experienced.
It can occur in all
ethnic and racial groups.
It is estimated that there are
around 700,000 people in the UK,
including one in 100 children,
diagnosed with autism spectrum
disorder according to the BMA in 2020.
Beth: Autism spectrum disorder is
a lifelong developmental condition,
related to brain development and affects
the way a child, young person or adult
responds to the world around them
and impacts how they perceive others.
Joe: On the whole individuals with
autism have untypical social interactions
or communication and may have some
restrictive and or repetitive behaviours.
However, the characteristics of autism
can vary so much from individual
to individual, especially depending
on where they are on the spectrum.
Beth: The way autism spectrum disorder
affects children and young people
can also change as they grow, develop
and experience different environments
and move through life’s major phases.
But they will, depending on where
they are on the spectrum, always need
some form of support to help them
throughout their life, especially
as they try to gain employment or
live independently within society.
Joe: So, we can see that although it
is a lifelong condition, there are
treatments and services that can help
to improve an individual’s symptoms
and ability to function better.
Special education and support
programmes can also help improve
their chances so that individuals
can reach their full potential and
secure the highest quality of life.
Beth: So let’s start to look a little
more into the condition of Autism and
work to increase our understanding.